Inventory to the Steve and Barbara Zeluck Papers TAM.549
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Steve and Barbara Zeluck Papers
1940s-2000s
1960-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Zeluck, Barbara, 1923-2010
Zeluck, Steve, 1922-1985
Tucker, Merry
Tucker, Paul
TAM.549
13 Linear Feet in 11 record cartons and 4 manuscript box.
Steve Zeluck (1922-1985) and Barbara Zeluck (1923-2010) were Trotskyist, labor union, and occupational health activists. Steve Zeluck was active in the rank and file caucus Chalk Dust, in the United Federation of Teachers (UFT), and also was active in the White Lung Association, a group that advocated for those made ill by their exposure to asbestosis (Zeluck died of mesothelioma). This unprocessed collection contains personal papers, including correspondence and writings, organizational records, printed ephemera, periodicals (some annotated), relating to the Zeluck's activism in the Trotskyist movement, including within the Socialist Workers Party, International Socialists, Workers Power, and Solidarity, and within the UFT, and the White Lung Association and other asbestos-related activity. The papers also document Barbara Zeluck's socialist feminist and women's health care activism. Most periodical titles have been transferred to the Library's print collection.
Arrangement
This unprocessed collection is arranged topically.
Biographical Note
Steve Zeluck (1922-1985) and Barbara Zeluck (1923-2010) were Trotskyists, and labor union, and occupational health activists. Steve Zeluck was active in the rank and file caucus Chalk Dust, in the United Federation of Teachers (UFT), and also was active in the White Lung Association, a group that advocated for those made ill by their exposure to asbestosis (Zeluck died of mesothelioma). Barbara Zeluck was also involved in socialist feminist actcivity, and in women's health care issues through the Coalition for Abortion Rights and Against Sterilization Abuse (CARASA). Former members of the Socialist Workers Party, they were also involved in the "Regroupment" efforts of the late 1970s-early 1980s to bring together several Trotskyist organizations. They left the SWP, and were successively involved in the Trotskyist groups International Socialists, Workers Power, and Solidarity.
Additional biographical information can be found in the following articles:
"In Memory of Steve Zeluck," by Lew Friedman (Against the Current, number 65, November-December 1996)
http://www.solidarity-us.org/node/2316
"Barbara Zeluck, 1923-2010." Against the Current, number 147, July-August 2010
http://www.solidarity-us.org/epublish/1/95
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Merry Tucker and Paul Tucker in 2010. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2010.066 and 2018.114.
Scope and Contents
This unprocessed collection contains correspondence and writings; organizational records, printed reports, position papers, circulars, printed ephemera, periodicals (some annotated), relating to the Zelucks' activism in the Trotskyist movement, including within the Socialist Workers Party, International Socialists, Workers Power, and Solidarity, and within the United Federation of Teachers, and the White Lung Association and other asbestos-related activity. The papers also document Barbara Zeluck's socialist feminist and women's health care activism. Most periodical titles have been separated and transferred to the Library's print collection.
NOTE: In addition to the box-level descriptions provided below, there is available at the Library, a more detailed contents listing that accompanied the donation. However, this listing does not conform to the current organization of the material.
Separated Materials
Numerous serials titles, including internal bulletins of the various socialist and Trotskyist groups in which the Zelucks were involved, have been transferred to the Library's serials holdings.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Trotskyists |z New York (State) |z New York.; Women socialists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Asbestosis |z United States.; Teachers' unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Trotskyism -- United States.; Socialist feminism.; Labor union democracy -- New York (State) -- New York.; Socialist parties -- United States.; Solidarity (Organization: U.S.); Zeluck, Barbara, 1923-2010; Zeluck, Steve, 1922-1985; Socialist Workers Party; White Lung Association; United Federation of Teachers; Chalk Dust (United Federation of Teachers); Tucker, Merry; Tucker, Paul
- Series I: Papers
  - Contains: Socialist Workers Party (SWP) Discussion Bulletins with handwritten notes; Essays regarding various topics such as American Imperialism, Marxism, Economics; the 1978 Energy Crisis artciles and other materials; Capital Shortage documents. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1940s - 1970s (Box 1)
  - Contains: Notes and essays on energy policy; essays on economic theory and war economy; marxist study materials; essays on unionism; essays on race in America and South Africa; On Third World Development by Steve Zeluck. Miscellaneous materials may also be found in two folders at the end of this box. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1960s - 1970s (Box 2)
  - Contains: "Regroupment" Issue (attempt at an alliance among several Trotskyist groups); International Socialists, Socialist Workers Party; Workers Power: reports, position papers, circulars, bulletins, notes, etc; Steve Zeluck on Portugal. Miscellaneous materials may also be found in two folders at the end of this box. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1970s - 1980s (Box 3, Box 17, Box 18)
  - Contains: "Regroupment" Issue Continued: Marxist-Feminist Study Group; Socialist-Feminism Resarch Files; Health Care Research Files; Solidarity (socialist organization) documents. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1970s - 1980s (Box 4)
  - Contains: Asbestos files; Solidarity mailings and convention materials; New York Committee for Occupational Safety and Health (NYCOSH) materials; White Lung Association (WLA) materials; Mealey's Litigation Reports on Asbestos; Various Union workbooks and reports. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1970s - 2000 (Box 5)
  - Contains: Solidarity mailings, convention materials, meeting minutes; White Lung Association correspondence, articles, notes; Folder of materials regarding 9/11's environmental impact; Articles on trade unionism, communism and radical economics. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1970s - 2000s (Box 6)
  - Contains: New York Committee for Occupation Safety and Health (NYCOSH) clippings and newsletters; Brian Wolfman correspondence; Susan Koniak articles; White Lung Association (WLA) meeting minutes; Asbestos Task Force materials. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1980s - 1990s (Box 7)
  - Contains: Workers safety materials, various countries; White Lung Association (WLA) legal materials;New York Committee for Occupation Safety and Health (New York Committee for Occupation Safety and Health (NYCOSH) materials; French translations of Deomocracie and Socialisme, and asbestos documents; Middle East materials; Articles about Maoism; Asbestos and union materials from other countries; International correspondence; Asbestos Victims of America (AVA) materials; Tobacco/Asbestos materials. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders Tobacco; Public Citizen, INFACT, 1940s - 2000s (Box 8)
  - Contains: White Lung Asbestos Information Center correspondence; BLOC Bill and Testimony re Brown and Black Lung: Newsletters, Clippings, Testimony; New York Committee for Occupation Safety and Health (NYCOSH) re Workers' Compensation Safety Representation; Clippings;Black Workers for Justice (BWFJ): Pamphlets. Miscellaneous materials may also be found in one folder at the end of this box. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1980s - 1990s (Box 9)
  - Contains: Saving Social Security materials; Asbestos Information: English and French; White Lung Information Center: Asbestos Update; Labor Party: Brochures, Correspondence, Flyers; Including New York City Dissolution, Complete Slate Flyers, etc.; Steve Zeluck Pamphlet: 'The UFT Strike: A Blow Against Teacher Unionism; New York Solidarity: Notes and Email Correspondence. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1990s - 2000s (Box 10)
  - Contains: African-American Liberation: research materials; Notes: China, Vietnam, Civil liberties, etc; Women and Liberation: pamphlets, clippings, notes; 1975 New York City Tax Reform and Fiscal Crisis; Early Solidarity materials: women's issues; articles about different economic theories. NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1970s - 1990s (Box 11)
  - Contains: Materials on Bureaucratic Collectivism; Article: Class Struggle and the Modernization of Capital in Portugal, 1974-1975; Deadly Corn: AIW Local 837's Campaign for Justice at the A.E. Staley Mfg. Company(Video (VHS)); An Unacceptable Level of Death and Tuner and Newell Video (VHS); Democracy Now!:The Great White Death-Asbestos( Audio Tape). NOTE: much of this material is not in folders, 1970s - 2000s (Box 12)
  - Contains: Research files and ephemera; Manuscripts, drafts, and notes for articles and papers; Convention and conference materials; Booklets, pamphlets, and newsletters; Meeting minutes and agendas, 1940s - 2000s (Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16)